A Guide to the Melinda E. Pittman Theatrical Collection, 1974-2012 (bulk, 1990-2008)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Melinda E. Pittman Theatrical Collection, 1974-2012 (bulk, 1990-2008)
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Pittman, Melinda E.
Ms2017-009
4.5 Cubic Feet; 6 boxes, 1 oversize folder
The collection includes scripts, songs, lyrics, production designs, directing and production notebooks, press, interviews, audio and video recordings, and other materials related to Melinda Pittman's theatrical career.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Melinda E. Pittman Theatrical Collection was donated to Special Collections in 2016.
Biographical Note
Melinda E. Pittman was born June 21, 1953 in Falls Church, Virginia. She graduated from Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University's (VPI&SU) Theatre Arts Department in 1975 with a Bachelor of Arts in Honors with Distinction. She then spent a year studying Theatre Directing at Tulane University in New Orleans, Louisiana before moving to Portland, Oregon. In Portland, Pittman worked with various theatrical companies including the Portland Labor Players II, The Fallen Angel Choir, and BroadArts Theatre. She received the 2000 Angus L. Bowmer Drama Award from the Oregon Book Awards for her show WonderBroads: The Babes & Broads Who Broke the Rules highlighting the contributions of women throughout history. In 2013, she received a Master of Arts in Interdisciplinary Studies focusing on Women's Social Justice Theatre from Marylhurst University in Marylhurst, Oregon.
Scope and Content
The collection includes scripts, songs, lyrics, production designs, directing and production notebooks, press, interviews, audio and video recordings, and other materials related to Melinda Pittman's theatrical career, including material about Pittman's original works Atlantis and WonderBroads. Also included are some alumni newsletters from the Virginia Tech Theatre Arts program and a copy of Pittman's Masters Thesis. The collection includes materials from 1974 to 2012 with the majority of material from the 1990's and 2000's. See the Arrangement note for additional information on the contents of the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in fourteen series. For the most part, the series reflect the arrangement in which the collection was received from the donor. Material is primarily organized by production company and show. Some items, including a copy of Pittman's screenplay, No Brainer, and her notes on non-profits and political action are not contained within one of the series.
Series I: University Records includes material from Pittman's time attending institutions of higher education. It has three sub-series: Virginia Polytechnic Institute & State University, Tulane University, and Marylhurst University.
Sub-Series I: Virginia Polytechnic Institute & State University includes material from Pittman's time at VPI&SU, including production notebooks for Pigeons and Chamber Music.
Sub-Series II: Tulane University includes material from Pittman's time at Tulane University, including material about productions of The Lover and The Country Wife.
Sub-Series III: Marylhurst University includes material from Pittman's time at Marylhurst University, including her masters thesis.
Series II: Oregon Shakespeare Festival Association includes material from various productions at the Oregon Shakespeare Festival, including The Breasts of Tiresius.
Series III: Theatre Workshop includes material from the Theatre Workshop production company including You Can't Take it With You, and The Real Inspector Hound. There is one sub-series: Power.
Series IV: Critical Mass Productions includes material from the Critical Mass Productions production of Bits and Pieces.
Series V: Portland Labor Players II includes material from various productions by the Portland Labor Players II company, including Season of Silence. There is one sub-series: 1934: Blood and Roses.
Series VI: Portland Civic Theatre includes material from the Portland Civic Theatre production of The Hot L Baltimore.
Series VII: Atlantis includes material from the original musical Atlantis written, composed, and directed by Pittman.
Series VIII: The Fallen Angel Choir includes material from Pittman's time as part of The Fallen Angel Choir, including many audio and video recordings.
Series IX: Summer Angels, Some Are Not! includes material from Pittman's time as part of the group Summer Angels, Some Are Not!, including many audio and video recordings.
Series X: AngelTime Productions, Inc. includes material from shows produced by AngelTime Productions, Inc. There are three sub-series: Paradise Flossed, Angels: The Next Generation, and Melinda & Angels DotComedy.
Series XI: WonderBroads includes material from Pittman's show WonderBroads, including different versions of the show, production books, marketing materials, video recordings, and correspondence with the Oregon Book Awards.
Series XII: BroadArts Theatre includes material from Pittman's production company BroadArts Theatre, including video recordings, notes on running the non-profit business, and material about the show Bunkin' With You in the Afterlife. There are seven sub-series: Read a Wild Tale, Homeland In-Security, Fat and Sassy, AmBushed!, If I Were Queen of the Forest, WonderBroader, and A/Broad for All Seasons.
Series XIII: Sheet Music includes copies of Pittman's original music, set lists from shows, popular music used in her parodies, and notes about lyrics.
Series XIV: Theatrical Career includes promotional materials, videos, audio recordings, headshots, résumés, press, and portfolios related to Pittman's career in the theatre.
Index Terms
Persons:
Pittman, Melinda E.
Corporate Names:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Dept. of Performing Arts and Communications; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Theatre Arts Department
Subjects:
Community theater; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Sheet music; Social justice
Geographical Names:
Portland (Or.)
Genre and Form Terms:
Political satire
- University Records
  - Virginia Polytechnic Institute & State University
    - Theatre Arts University Theatre, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Headshots, c.1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Pigeons production notebook, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chamber Music production notebook, Spring 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chamber Music production script, Spring 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tulane University
    - The Lover, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - The Country Wife, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Marylhurst University
    - Laugh the World Awake: Toward a Declaration of Liberation Comedy - Master's Thesis, 2013-06-08 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Oregon Shakespeare Festival Association
  - Programs, photos, and correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Breasts of Tiresius, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Theatre Workshop
  - You Can't Take it With You
    - Directing notes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Production script, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Press, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - The Miracle Worker program, c.1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - The Real Inspector Hound programs and press, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Charley's Aunt program, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Power
    - Production notebook, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photos, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Press, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Show poster, 1983 (Folder 1)
- Critical Mass Productions
  - Bits and Pieces production script, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bits and Pieces press, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bits and Pieces photos, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bits and Pieces show poster, 1983 (Folder 1)
- Portland Labor Players II
  - Season of Silence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1934: Blood and Roses
    - Press, research, and marketing, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Program, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Scenic design painting, 1982 (Folder 1)
    - Show poster, 1982 (Folder 1)
  - Brecht in the Eighties, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Press and show posters, 1981-1982 (Folder 1)
- Portland Civic Theatre
  - The Hot L Baltimore, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Atlantis
  - Script, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Directing notebook, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Watercolor costume design, c.1983 - 1984 (Folder 1)
  - Production notes, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Production notebook, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Press, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Show poster, 1984 (Folder 1)
- The Fallen Angel Choir
  - Press and marketing, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Christmas Wrap / Clanging Bells (45 RPM record), 1986, 1 45rpm Record in a sleeve (2 copies) (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - The Fallen Angel Choir (Audio Recording), 1986 (Box 5)
  - The Fallen Angel Choir (Video Recording), Summer 1987, 1 VHS tape (box 6); 1 DVD (box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Happy Trails Tour P.S.U. (Video Recording), 1989-12, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Fallen Angels Tour 90 (Video Recording), 1990, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Angels XVII: Abducted by Aliens, Also: Holiday Spirit and Good Evening Show (Video Recording), 1992-12-22, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Angels XVII: Abducted by Aliens (Audio Recording), 1992, 1 Audio Cassette (Box 5)
  - Middle Aged Mystery Tour (Audio Recording), 1993, 1 Audio Cassette (Box 5)
  - Still Fallen After All These Years (Audio Recording), 1995, 1 Audio Cassette (Box 5)
  - Bleeding Hearts Club Band (Video Recording ADAT), 1995-12-16, 6 VHS Tapes (Box 6)
  - It's A Wrap! (Video Recording), 1996, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Wake Up and Smell the Angels (Video Recording), c.1993 - 1995, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Show posters, 1986-1996 (Folder 1)
- Summer Angels, Some Are Not!
  - Press and marketing, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Summer Angels, Some Are Not! (Audio Recording), 1991-04-19-1991-04-20, 1 Audio Cassette (Box 5)
  - Demo: Boomers With a View (Video Recording), 1993, 1 VHS tape (Box 6)
  - L'Aftershocks (Video Recording), 1994-05, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - L'Aftershocks (Audio Recording), 1994, 1 Audio Cassette (Box 5)
  - It's Their Party... demo (Audio Recording), 1995, 1 Audio Cassette (Box 5)
  - Rebels in a Minivan (Audio Recording), 1996, 1 CD (Box 5)
- AngelTime Productions, Inc.
  - Paradise Flossed
    - Production book, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Sheet music, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Notes, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Press and marketing, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Photos, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Paradise Flossed (Video Recording), 1997, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
    - Paradise Flossed demo (Video Recording), 1997, 1 VHS tape (Box 6)
    - Paradise Flossed (Audio Recording), 1997, 1 CD (2 copies) (Box 5)
  - Angels: The Next Generation
    - Fallin' Angels Next Gen with Les Sarnoff Dolby B NR (Audio Recording), 1997-12-02, 1 Audio Cassette (Box 5)
    - Frank-N-Sensitive Comedy Christmas Carols, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Frank-N-Sensitive Comedy Christmas Carols (Audio Recording), 1997, 1 CD; 1 Audio Cassette (Box 5)
    - Angels: The Next Generation full show (Video Recording), 1997-12-20, 1 VHS tape (Box 6)
    - Bring in 'Da Toys, Bring in 'Da Bunk, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Bring in 'Da Toys, Bring in 'Da Bunk production book, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Angel's Secret Santa Survivor Holiday Gametime, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - It's a WonderBroad Life, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Press and marketing, c.1997 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Photos, c.1997 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Show posters, 1997 (Folder 1)
  - Melinda & Angels DotComedy
    - It's a Jingle Out There production book, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - It's a Jingle Out There first show draft, 1999-10-20 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - It's a Jingle Out There draft, 1999-11-01 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Melinda & Angels DotComedy promotional video (Video Recording), c.1998 - 1999, 1 VHS tape (Box 6)
- WonderBroads
  - Production book, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Shortened version, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notes and research, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photos, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Press and marketing, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Promotional video (Video Recording), 2000, 1 VHS tape (2 copies) (Box 6)
  - Demo (Video Recording), 2002-06, 1 VHS tape (2 copies) (Box 6)
  - Notes, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 2003 Production, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 2007 Production, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Oregon Book Awards correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Jobs With Justice 10th Anniversary Dinner and Awards Presentation, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - WonderBroads: The Babes and Broads Who Broke the Rules (Audio Recording), 2001, 1 CD (Box 5)
- BroadArts Theatre
  - Read a Wild Tale
    - Drafts, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Second Draft (Digital File), 2001-04-08, READ A WILD TALE2.doc file on 3.5" floppy disc. (74kb) (Box 5)
  - Homeland In-Security
    - Notebook, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Drafts, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Press, marketing, and correspondence, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Photos, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Show poster, 2002 (Folder 1)
    - Homeland In-Security (Video Recording), 2002-02, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Fat and Sassy
    - Script, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Production book, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Performance script, 2003-11-18 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Photos, notes, and marketing, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Sheet music, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Press, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Fat and Sassy II (Video Recording), 2009-11-13, 1 DVD (Box 5)
  - AmBushed!
    - Production notebook, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 2005 script, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Marketing, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - If I Were Queen of the Forest
    - Production book, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Song lyrics, photos, press, and marketing, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Show poster, 2006 (Folder 1)
  - WonderBroader
    - Research, c.2008 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Research, c.2008 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence, c.2008 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Marketing, c.2008 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - BroadArts Theatre IWD Concert at Urban Grind (Video Recording), 2009-03-07, 1 DVD (Box 5)
  - A/Broad for All Seasons
    - Production book, 2009-2010 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Drafts and notes, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Marketing, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Show poster, 2010 (Folder 1)
  - Bunkin' With You in the Afterlife, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - BroadArts Peace Salon (Video Recording), 2002-10-12, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - Grant writing and fund raising workshop, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - BroadArts Theatre Visionary Salon Series grant application, c.2008 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - BroadArts Theatre, Inc. notes, c.2012 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - BroadArts Theatre demo tape (Video Recording), 2000, 2002, 2004, 1 VHS tape (Box 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes clips from Fat and Sassy, WonderBroads, and Homeland In-Security.
- Sheet Music
  - Titles beginning with A-E, 1984-2012 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Titles beginning with F-H, 1984-2012 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Titles beginning with I-L, 1984-2012 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Titles beginning with M-S, 1984-2012 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Titles beginning with T-Y, 1984-2012 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Set lists, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Popular music, 1931-1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notes on lyrics without titles, c1990's (Box 3, Folder 5)
- No Brainer Screenplay, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Theatrical Career
  - Comedy press and marketing, c.1989 - 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Comedy marketing, c.1990's (Folder 1)
  - General press and marketing, c.1976 - 1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General press and marketing, c.1976 - 1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Scenes from Power and Hot L Baltimore, Interviews with Melinda - Director (Video Recording), c.1985, 1 VHS tape (Box 6); 1 DVD (Box 5) (Box 5, Box 6)
  - General marketing photos, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Headshots and resumés, c.1989 - 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Western Regional CTA Conference photos (Digital Files), 2012-05-18-2012-05-20, 1 CD with 49 JPG files (Box 5)
  - Male Fantasy Beer (Video Recording), 1997, 1 VHS tape (Box 6)
  - Directing and acting portfolio, 1980-1992 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Rose City Park Neighborhood History Book 100th Anniversary, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General correspondence, 1996 - 1999, c.2010, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Notes on Non-Profits and Political Action, c.1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Astrological Reading (Audio Recording), 2011-06-28, 1 DVD (Box 5)
- Northwest Peace Festival Poster, 1983 (Folder 1)